Guide to the Larry Townsend Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Larry Townsend collection
1972-1999
MS 1975
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(5 boxes)
The collection consists of publications authored, compiled by, or edited by Larry Townsend and published by his publishing house, L. T. Publications. The publications include fiction and comics and are illustrated with drawings and photographs. The collection also includes works by others, including catalogs for products for the leather lifestyle, comics, a manual, and an autobiographical work. A few of these items include letters and inscriptions to Townsend. The publications document the gay male leather community and sadomasochistic sexual practices through fiction, nonfiction, drawings, photographs, and product catalogs.
Townsend, Larry
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by author and title.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of publications authored, compiled by, or edited by Larry Townsend and published by his publishing house, L. T. Publications. The publications include fiction and comics and are illustrated with drawings and photographs. The collection also includes works by others, including catalogs for products for the leather lifestyle, comics, a manual, and an autobiographical work. A few of these items include letters and inscriptions to Townsend. The publications document the gay male leather community and sadomasochistic sexual practices through fiction, nonfiction, drawings, photographs, and product catalogs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Librarian for Gay and Lesbian Studies, 2010.
Biographical / Historical
Larry Townsend (pseudonym for Bernhardt) was born on October 27, 1930. He served in the U.S. Air Force from 1950-1954. He received a Bachelor of Arts degree from the University of California, Los Angeles, in 1957, and pursued graduate study at the State University of California, Los Angeles. He became involved in the leather community of Los Angeles in the early 1960s and became an activist in the late 1960s, serving as the president of the "Homophile Effort for Legal Protection" in 1972. As a novelist, photographer, and publisher, he both chronicled and shaped the gay leather community from the late 1960s to 2008, the year of his death. He authored many books and articles on leather and sadomasochism, including The Leatherman's Handbook, published in 1971. Additionally, he published his own work, as well as that of others, through his publishing house, L. T. Publications. Many of his works have been reprinted by other publishers. Townsend died on July 29, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Bondage (Sexual behavior); Gay men -- Fiction; Gay men -- Sexual behavior -- Fiction; Gay men -- Sexual behavior; Homosexuality; Leather lifestyle; Sadomasochism -- Fiction; Sadomasochism; Sexual dominance and submission; LGBTQ resource; Townsend, Larry
- Books authored or edited by Townsend
  - 7 tales of whips, slaves & retribution, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Stories by Victor Terry, Jeff Kincaid, and others.
  - Anthology of S&M, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Art of Tom "Ropes" McGurk, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beware the god who smiles, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Bondage photos of Tom "Ropes" McGurk, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chains, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Construction worker, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Contest book, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Disziplin extra: das beste von Larry Townsend, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Faustus contract, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Fledermaus anthology, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Four SM tales of experimentation, punishment & revenge, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Stories by Jeff Kincaid and Rob, illustrations by Sean and Zane, bondage photos by Don Russo.
  - The Lance/Jeff Kincaid SM, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Larry Townsend Presents Masters: a collection of male-to-male SM stories, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Larry Townsend Presents Studbusters II, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Stories by Jeff Kincaid.
  - Larry Townsend's book of men in bondage: a collection of the best photographs from his early books, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Larry Townsend's favorite bondage photos, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Larry Townsend's photo collection, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Larry Townsend's second book of men in bondage, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Leather AD volume 1.M and volume 2.S, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Leather AD_S, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Leatherman's workbook, Vols. III-V, 1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Leatherman's workbook, Vols. 6-8, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Long leather cord, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Macbeth: the bloody tower, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Mack anthology, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Man sword, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mind Master, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - More dungeons, more barns and more slaves, [1987] (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Mockup copy, with several pieces cut out but present.
  - More dungeons, more barns and more slaves errata, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - New treasury of SM, Vols. 1-5, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Of slaves & ropes & lovers, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Potpourri of S&M, Vols. 1-5, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Power gods 2+2, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rituals of the gag: a collection of SM stories, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Illustrated by Sean and Rob.
  - Run, little leather boy, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Illustrations by Zane, photographs by Townsend.
  - Run no more, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Mockup of first issue with several pieces cut out and missing.
  - Run no more, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - School master and other stories of SM at school, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Slaves, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - SM contrasts, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - An SM scrapbook, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - SM scrapbook 2, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - SM/SD: a collection of 5 stories by Victor Terry, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Tales of arrogance, whips & humiliation, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Tales of discipline, obedience & submission, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Tales of servitude & surrender, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - To take a slave, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - A Treasury of S&M, Nos. 1, 3, 6, 8-9, 1975-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 2-6)
  - Two tales of SM fantasy & magic, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Whitewater run, a leather SM adventure by Victor Terry, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Books authored by others
  - The Hun (Schmeling, Bill)
    - Gohr: a tale of the new age #2, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Inscribed to Townsend and signed by the author.
    - The Hun book of bondage, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Inscribed to Townsend by the author.
    - Hun Comics, Iss. 1-3, 5-7, 9-1, 1996-1999 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      All but issue 9 inscribed to Townsend by the author.
  - J.W., Overtime parking, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - J. D., The Return of the Coney Island Knights, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Typed letter signed from the publisher to Townsend tipped in.
  - Man's Hand Films, Catalog, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Man's Hand Films presents spanking, an anthology, Vols. I-IV, 1991-1992, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Man's Hand Films presents spanking, an anthology, Vols. V-VII, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mr. Fetters, the catalog, parts one and two (2 volumes), 1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mr. S Leather, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Old Reliable audio cassette tale library catalogue, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Old Reliable solo videotape catalogue, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Old Reliable wrestling catalogue, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - R.F.M., The Life of a masochist, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Rob Amsterdam [catalogue], 1985 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Sean
    - Biff, Nos. 1-2, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Bigfoot and a half! The enigma of the northwest, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Nine-sheet unbound comic inscribed to Townsend by the author.
  - Stephen
    - Adventure time, Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Mockup with publishing data stapled to rear wrap.
    - Adventure time, collector's edition, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Ward, R. Gary, The Coney Island Knights, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Wiseman, Jay, SM 101, a realistic introduction, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Zeus Collection (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - 1984 Mr Zeus contest issue (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Sado island, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Zeus, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Zeus collector's edition, Vol. 1, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 15)